Do I have to diet and work out on TRT?
Because that's um yeah, that's an advice
we give uh very often.
I mean, yeah, because you you're looking
for TRT for lifestyle optimization.
That's it. I I don't feel good. I want
to feel better. And so, I would say the
best way to feel better and it's free is
looking after yourself properly and
exercising. And I would say anyone, no
matter who you are, needs to do that.
And most of the patients seem to get
that. I mean, in for TRT, they're all
men. Most of them want to be fitter and
stronger. That pretty much is the
driving force for them seeking help. So,
kind of I don't find that a difficult
discussion to have. There's only a
couple of times where patients have put
up resistance to it. But I do make clear
that I expect you to live a healthier
lifestyle than perhaps most people. I do
expect you to like stop recreational
drugs completely. They definitely
contribute to lowering your
testosterone. If you drink too much, I I
do expect you to stop drinking or be
completely in control of that. Um, some
people don't think they binge drink. And
it doesn't actually take that much
alcohol to binge drink. And it's pretty
easy to reach, say, 40 units a week
without trying that hard, especially if
you go out and drink socially. It can be
done. So, I am quite clear with those
patient. I expect you to stop doing
that. I expect you to take steps towards
stop smoking and vaping and all of this.
Um, and just live a textbook healthy
lifestyle. And that's what I think will
get the most from it because if if I've
got your numbers right and you're still
not feeling good, I'm I'm I'm pretty
much out of ideas. There's there are
other things going on that you can sort
out yourself, but that's kind of it. TRT
is not this like silver bullet that will
fix everything. It will just fix your
low testosterone and quite a lot of it
is up to you. I think
so TRT or HRT is not just the cherry on
top. uh you do expect the patient to do
a lot of work themselves. Yeah,
absolutely. I'm pretty clear about that.
I'm quite lucky in that most of my
patients are pretty keen to do that.
Most doctors when they see patients that
that perhaps are overweight, they they
actually don't want to change that or
they're insistent that they exercise
when when really they're probably not.
Um they don't want to change their diet.
Whereas I think most of the TRT
community are actually very keen on
improving their lifestyle. So is that
that makes my job pretty easy that but I
think if we're talking to a wider
audience which obviously this is being
broadcasted to I would say absolutely
and and if you're not optimizing that
part before you're seeking TRT
absolutely do it. Stop drinking
completely. TRT is not something you
should be seeking. It's something to
optimize your health if you need it.
Stop drinking. Stop smoking. Improve
your diet. Um get a good workout regime
going. Um it doesn't even need to be
exact. just get some sort of
weightlifting going. It doesn't need to
be advanced. You're not competing. And
get some sort of cardio in there as
well. And I would I would actually
expect most young men to try and get
their lifestyle better to exercise
almost every day. I don't think five
times a week's a lot to ask for a young
man to train. It should really be the
baseline that you should be doing
something. Um so most of my patients
that have come to me have already done
all of this. they um and and to be
honest, if you haven't, I would really
encourage you to not spend more money
and actually try this yourself and come
back to me. And I've said that to a lot
of patients as well. So yeah, it it
seems a bit I don't like to be
inflexible as a doctor. I like to try
and listen to people, but for that one
that that really is a non-negotiable for
me. I think you really do need to try.
Yeah, you gave some specifics about um
cardiovascular and resistance training.
Um but what about diet? What do you mean
if you say to a patient you have to
watch your diet?
What do you recommend? Um I tend not to
go into too much in specifics about I'm
not an expert basically. So someone who
does one sport will go well that diet
wouldn't work for me. So if you're an
ultramarathon runner, you would eat you
eat masses of food and you do things
differently. If you want to be a
powerlifter, then you need to adjust
your diet accordingly as well.
Personally, I'm a fan of um sort of low
carbs if you can, high protein, high
good fats. And I do sometimes tell
patients, do your own research, but high
protein doesn't mean you can get protein
from literally any source and have fun
with it. It doesn't mean eat an entire
plate of sausages. That's completely
different protein source to say lean
chicken. They're not the same. So, um
you do need to look into what these
healthy fats are. You need to look in a
bit into your diet and take your own
interest because I don't have the
educational background to talk about
every sport and the nutrition. It's very
specialist and we'd be here all day if I
was going to do that. It's a completely
separate topic. So, um but as a as a
general thing, I'd say no processed
foods. If it's made in a factory, don't
touch it. Um, go look get your get your
meat from a butcher if you can, that
sort of thing. So, you can see what it
is. It's no one's done anything
artificial to it. Um, good amounts of
fruit and veg. I know there are some
people out there with carnivore diets
who saying fruit and veg is the enemy
and things like that. Personally, I
don't I think it's pretty good source of
nutrition, I think. But like, um, so
that sort of stuff, I mean, if you eat
fruit, veg, nuts, uh, lean meats, I
don't think you can go too far wrong, to
be honest.
Hey everybody.